Some legends can never be tamed.
Spirit: Stallion of the Cimarron is a animation,
adventure, family film directed by Kelly Asbury.
A captured mustang remains determined to return to his herd no matter what.
Spirit (voice), played by Matt Damon.
The Colonel (voice), played by James Cromwell.
Little Creek (voice), played by Daniel Studi.
Sgt. Adams (voice), played by Chopper Bernet.
Murphy / Railroad Foreman (voice), played by Jeff LeBeau.
Soldier (voice), played by John Rubano.
Spirit: Stallion of the Cimarron (or simply Spirit) is a 2002 American animated Western film directed by Kelly Asbury and
Lorna Cook, written by John Fusco, from an idea by Jeffrey Katzenberg, who produced with Mireille Soria.
Produced by DreamWorks Animation, the film combines
traditional animation and computer animation.
Set in the Old West in the late 19th century, the film follows Spirit, a Kiger mustang stallion (voiced by Matt Damon as a narrator), who is captured during the
American Indian Wars by the United States Cavalry; he is eventually freed by a Lakota man named Little Creek with whom he bonds, as well as a mare named Rain.
In contrast to the anthropomorphic style of animal characters in other animated features, Spirit and his fellow horses communicate with
each other through non-linguistic sounds and body language (albeit with many human facial expressions and reactions).
Spirit: Stallion of the Cimarron was released in theaters
on May 24, 2002, by DreamWorks Pictures.
The film received mixed reviews from critics and grossed $122
million worldwide against a budget of $80 million.
It was nominated for the Academy Award for Best Animated Feature.
The film also launched a media franchise completely using computer animation, with a Netflix spin-off television series Spirit Riding Free
premiering on May 5, 2017, followed by  a spin-off of the original film, titled Spirit Untamed, released on June 4, 2021.
The film explores themes of freedom, villain, mustang, rivalry, wildlife.
The tone is emotional.